Alvin Romansky Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Alvin Romansky Papers
1907-1994
Romansky, Alvin
Mr. Romansky was a native Houstonian who practiced law. This set of papers documents his philanthropy and tremendous civic contribution to the contemporary art scene in Houston. Included also, is evidence of the social and civic contributions of his Uncle Thomas Flaxman.
4 boxes, 1 oversize folder; 3.1 linear feet
1968-001
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Alvin Sylvan Romansky was born in Houston, Texas on March 15, 1907, the only child of Joseph L. Romansky and Kate Flaxman. Following his childhood in Houston, he attended the Wharton School of Commerce and Finance at the University of Pennsylvania, the University of Texas at Austin, and the Houston Law School, where he received an LLB (Bachelor of Laws) degree in 1929.
Romansky remained in Houston to practice law. He was a member of the Texas State Bar Association, the American Bar Association, and the Commercial Law League of America.
In 1948, Romansky and five others chartered the Contemporary Arts Association, a non-profit organization founded to present exhibits of contemporary art to supplement the more traditional art shown at the Museum of Fine Arts. In 1949, the Association became the Contemporary Arts Museum, with its own building. Romansky served as Vice President of the Contemporary Arts Association/Museum from 1947-1952.
An art patron and collector, Romansky favored French graphics, contemporary French art, and Ashanti objects. He arranged the Rufino Tamayo exhibit and the Contemporary in Cotton exhibit at the Contemporary Arts Museum, and Ashanti Goldwrights exhibit at the University of Texas, as well as many others. He was also active in the Lithography Department of the Glassell School of Art. He donated a collection of graphics to the University of Texas, and an Alvin Romansky Print Room to the Museum of Fine Arts. Romansky was appointed a Life Trustee by the Museum of Fine Arts.
In addition, Romansky served as "Lieutenant Colonel" on the staff of Governor Miriam "Ma" Ferguson between 1933 and 1935, representing the State of Texas at official functions. He was co-founder of the Harris County Heritage Society, and drafted its original charter. He also served as a member of the Chancellor's Council of the University of Texas at Austin. Alvin Romansky was married to his wife Ethel for nineteen years. He died on March 14, 1994.
Sources: Contemporary Arts Museum. Handbook of Texas Online.
http://www.tsha.utexas.edu/handbook/online/ (3 May 2001).
Who's Who in American Art. 11th edition. New York: R.R. Bowker Co., 1973.
1994. Deaths. Houston Chronicle. 15 March (B).
Scope and Contents
The Alvin Romansky Papers include photographs, correspondence, documents, printed materials, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia related to the life and civic pursuits of Alvin Romansky, his father Joseph Romansky, and his uncle Thomas Flaxman. The bulk of the material (principally that related to Alvin Romansky) dates from the 1950s, but a significant amount of material related to Thomas Flaxman dates from the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
The first two boxes in the collection contain loose papers and photographs. Material related to Alvin Romansky comes first in these boxes, followed by material related to Thomas Flaxman, and then material related to Joseph Romansky. The third box holds a silver loving cup presented to Thomas Flaxman by the Directors of No-tsu-oh Association. The fourth box holds portions of two scrapbooks.
Two publications were removed from this collection and cataloged:
The Houston clubber. Houston, Tex.: Houston Club, 1958. Spec Coll HS2725.H68 H684
The new Houston Club. Houston, Tex.: The Club, [1955]. Spec Coll Ovs HS2725.H68 H68 1955
Special Collections holds a large number of materials that were donated to the department by Alvin Romansky, including rare books, and art books and catalogues. In addition, Special Collections also holds a large collection of fine art prints which were donated by Alvin Romansky. A large sub-collection of these prints are cartoons from the French Third Empire and the Franco-Prussian War.
The Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution, also holds some microfilmed material on Alvin Romansky. Included is a transcript of a recorded interview with Romansky, conducted by the Archives of American Art. For more information, see their web site:
http://artarchives.si.edu/start.htm
Subjects (Persons)
Romansky, Alvin; Romansky, Joseph; Flaxman, Thomas
Subjects (Organizations)
Contemporary Arts Association; Contemporary Arts Museum; Houston Country Club
Subjects
No-Tsu-Oh
Formats
Correspondence; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Clippings
Acquisition
Donated by Mr. Romansky in 1968 and 1969
Detailed Description
- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  This series includes correspondence from various people to Alvin Romansky, arranged alphabetically by sender. Notable correspondents include Oveta Culp Hobby, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Coke R. Stevenson.
  - Alvin Romansky, Note from Tom Connally, Oct. 14, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alvin Romansky, Letter from Oveta Culp Hobby, March 23, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alvin Romansky, Telegram from Josef Israels, Aug. 18, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alvin Romansky, Letter from Lyndon B. Johnson, November 14, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alvin Romansky, Letter from Richard F. Roper, January 26, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alvin Romansky, Letter from Alfred E. Smith, May 5, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alvin Romansky, Letter from Coke R. Stevenson, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alvin Romansky, Letter from Albert Thomas, March 23, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alvin Romansky, Printed European Christmas cards, 1960-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Alvin Romansky Memorabilia (Box 1, OVS)
  This series is comprised of photographs, documents, and clippings related to Alvin Romansky, which are arranged chronologically, with the exception of two unidentified photographs (Folders 14 and 15) that have been placed at the end. Included are a baby picture of Alvin Romansky, a printed program from a Houston memorial service for Warren G. Harding, and the charter of the Harris County Heritage Society. A 1924 diploma from the Prosso Preparatory School is in an oversized folder.
  - Alvin Romansky, [ca. 1907] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alvin Romansky, August 10, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alvin Romansky, 1924 (Box OVS)
  - Alvin Romansky, 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alvin Romansky, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alvin Romansky, May 1, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alvin Romansky, June 9, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alvin Romansky, [ca. 1950] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alvin Romansky, [ca. 1950] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Alvin Romansky, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Alvin Romansky, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Alvin Romansky, [19th century] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Alvin Romansky, [ca. 1940] (Box 1, Folder 21)
- European Art Trip (Box 1, Folder 22-46)
  This series consists of black and white snapshots taken during a trip to France and Italy. Most of the photographs record visits to the printing workshops of Fernand Mourlot, Georges Visat, and Maeght. Also included are an image of Pablo Picasso's ceramics and pottery kiln in France, and one of Friedensreich Hundertwasser and his wife.
  - European Art Trip, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - European Art Trip, May 1, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - European Art Trip, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - European Art Trip, June/July 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - European Art Trip, Nov. 27, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - European Art Trip, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - European Art Trip, March 1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - European Art Trip, ca. 1950's (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - European Art Trip, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- African Art Exhibit, Museum of Fine Arts, Houston (Box 1, Folder 47-52)
  This series contains black and white snapshots of displays of African sculpture from an exhibit at the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston.
  - African Art Exhibit, March 1959 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - African Art Exhibit, March 1959 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - African Art Exhibit, March 1959 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - African Art Exhibit, March 1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - African Art Exhibit, March 1959 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - African Art Exhibit, March 1959 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Joseph Romansky (Box 1, Folder 53-55)
  This series contains two photographs and a photocopied obituary for Joseph L. Romansky, Alvin Romansky's father. Joseph Romansky worked for the Flaxman Dry Goods Co., which was owned by his brother-in-law, Thomas Flaxman.
  - Joseph Romansky, ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Joseph Romansky, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Joseph Romansky, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Thomas Flaxman (Box 1, 3, Folder 56-76)
  This series contains materials related to Thomas Flaxman, who was Alvin Romansky's uncle. At various times, Flaxman was president of Flaxman Dry Goods, head of the Port Houston Land and Townsite Company, and vice-president of the Houston Farms Development Company. Flaxman was also a founder of the Houston Country Club and the Houston Club, served on numerous civic boards, and was general manager of No-Tsu-Oh, an annual Mardi Gras-style carnival held in Houston before World War I.
  Included are photographs, copies of newspaper clippings, the memorial book from Thomas Flaxman's memorial service, and a tablet with biographical or autobiographical notes about Thomas Flaxman. No-Tsu-Oh materials include a report from the directors of the 1914 Deep Water Festival, a sheet of stationery from that festival, and a silver loving cup that was presented to Thomas Flaxman. Also included are a number of photographs of the Houston Country Club, and the Houston Golf Club which formerly stood on its site.
  - Thomas Flaxman, [1897] (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Thomas Flaxman, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Thomas Flaxman, Sept. 25, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Thomas Flaxman, Nov. 25, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Thomas Flaxman, March 1965 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Thomas Flaxman, [1965] (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Thomas Flaxman, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Thomas Flaxman, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Thomas Flaxman: No-Tsu-Oh and Other Fairs, January 1914 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Thomas Flaxman: No-Tsu-Oh and Other Fairs, June 30, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Thomas Flaxman: No-Tsu-Oh and Other Fairs, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Thomas Flaxman: No-Tsu-Oh and Other Fairs, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Thomas Flaxman: No-Tsu-Oh and Other Fairs, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Country Club, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Country Club, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Country Club, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Country Club, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Country Club, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Country Club, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Club, June 18-22, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Thomas Flaxman: Houston Club, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Thomas Flaxman: No-Tsu-Oh (Loving Cup) (Box 3)
- Scrapbook (Box 2, 4, Folder 1-31)
  This series contains materials from two scrapbooks compiled by Alvin Romansky. Because the scrapbooks were fragile and in poor condition, most of the materials have been removed and placed in acid-free folders. Intact portions of two scrapbooks with their original newspaper clippings may be found in Box 4.
  The scrapbook series includes the original charter and by-laws of the Contemporary Arts Association, photographs of modern furniture and silverware, exhibit catalogs and local arts publications, and many newspaper clippings. The clippings have been photocopied onto acid-free paper for preservation purposes.
  - Scrapbook: Correspondence, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook: Contemporary Arts Association, 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook: Contemporary Arts Association, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook: Contemporary Arts Association, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook: Contemporary Arts Association, ca. 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook: Houston Exhibits, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook: Photographs, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook: Exhibits - Catalogs, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook: Exhibits - Catalogs, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook: Local Art Publications, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook: Local Art Publications, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook: Local Art Publications, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook: Local Art Publications, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook: Congregation Beth Israel, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook: Miscellaneous, ca. 1950's (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, 1933-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Scrapbook: Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook (Box 4)